Guide to the Robert Opie Shepherd Papers Relating to the Democratic Socialists of America, 1982-1990 AIS.1990.21
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Robert Opie Shepherd Papers Relating to the Democratic Socialists of America
1982-1990
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Shepherd, Robert Opie
AIS.1990.21
2.5 Linear Feet
The majority of the collection consists of notebooks recorded by Robert Opie Shepherd, conference materials, event announcements, and publications originating from both local and national sources.
History
Members of the New American Movement and the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee merged in 1982, forming the Democratic Socialists of America. The main goals of the movement reflected a desire to create a socialist presence in modern society. The purpose of the various projects and events of the Democratic Socialists was to develop strategies and to educate people. The socialist vision promoted by the movement was one of "feminism, racial equality, labor activism, equitable distribution, non-oppressive relationships, and the popular control of resources and production."
Robert Opie Shepherd became a member of the Pittsburgh Chapter of the New American Movement (NAM) in 1973. This chapter became the Democratic Socialists of America Pittsburgh Local in 1983 after the merger. Robert Opie shepherd actively participated in several DSA committees, projects, and conventions; he recorded minutes of meetings and notes of various DSA events. He served as the 1990 chairperson for the Pittsburgh Local, delegate to several DSA conferences, and as a member of a Democratic Socialists of America fact-finding Nicaraguan tour during January 1983.
Scope and Content Notes
The majority of the collection consists of notebooks recorded by Robert Opie Shepherd, conference materials, event announcements, and publications originating from both local and national sources. The collection contains detailed notes and items relevant to Robert Opie Shepherd's active participation in the DSA. He participated in many local events sponsored or supported by the DSA and the Pittsburgh Local. These included voter registration, Women's Day, the Chinese students' democracy movement, and the April 15th Coalition. national DSA projects include the Working Group on Health Care, the American Solidarity Campaign, and various boycotts and rallies to promote socialist issues. He also collected information regarding Michael Harrington (1928 - 1989), founder and former co-chair of the DSA.
As a delegate representing the Pittsburgh Local, he obtained materials from the 1984 regional DSA conferences in Mechanicsburg and Bloomsburg, Pennsylvania. He also collected delegate materials from the 1983 New York, 1984 Philadelphia, 1989 Baltimore, and 1990 Youth National DSA conventions. As a member of the 1983 Nicaraguan delegation, Robert Opie Shepherd recorded and collected information regarding the political and social condition of that country. Included is a series of educational pamphlets regarding health and personal hygiene issued by the Ministerio de Salud of Nicaragua, as well as several brief historical biographies.
The collection contains a series of the Pittsburgh Local's publication, the Allegheny Socialist, and the national Democratic Socialists of America Publication, the Democratic Left. Publications were issued by specific DSA commissions, such as the Environmental, Labor, Religion, Youth, Latino, Afro-American, and Anti-racism Commissions. Robert Opie Shepherd obtained newsletters of DSA locals in Cleveland, Chicago, New York, Kentucky, Central Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, and Reading. Also present are issues of the Socialist Forum, published by the Institute for Democratic Socialism.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert Opie Shepherd in 1990.
Previous Citation
Robert Opie Shepherd Papers Relating to the Democratic Socialists of America, AIS.1990.21, Archives Services Center, University of Pittsburgh.
Politics; Social action; Personal papers; Nicaragua -- Politics and government -- 1979-1990; Socialism -- United States; Socialism -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Political parties -- United States; Political parties -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Democratic Socialists of America. Pittsburgh Chapter; Democratic Socialists of America; Harrington, Michael; Institute for Democratic Socialism (U.S.); New American Movement (Organization). Pittsburgh Chapter; East End Food Co-op (Pittsburgh, Pa.); New American Movement (Organization); Nicaragua. Ministerio de Salud
- Notebooks Recorded by Robert Opie Shepherd, 1983-1990; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The notebooks contain unofficial minutes of DSA Local meetings, committee meetings and conference notes. They provide detailed accounts of specific DSA meetings, although the official and complete records of the Pittsburgh Local are not present.
  - Notebook, October 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Contains notes from National Executive Committee Plenaries, a list of Local Chapter members attending, and notes for DSA Songbook.
  - Notebooks, April 1983-November 1984, January 1984-February 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Contains notes from Jobs with Peace Lunch, a review of Wildsisters, East End Food Co-Op annual meeting, DSA/Pittsburgh meeting.
  - Notebooks, March 1984-January 1985, February 1985-June 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Contains DSA/Pittsburgh meetings, local committee meetings, and project planning meetings.
  - Notebook, November 1984-December 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Contains notes DSA National Convention in Philadelphia.
  - Notebooks, August 1984 and January 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Contains notes from committee meetings, Statewide Organization meeting, Cultural and Education Roundtable, DSA National Directions, and Statewide Jobs with Peace meetings.
  - Miscellaneous notes by Robert Opie Shepherd, July 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Contains DSA/Pittsburgh meetings, calendar of events, notes from Michael Harrington lecture, discussion group, and convention travel costs.
- Bylaws and Constitution, 1983; II.
  - Bylaws of DSA/Pittsburgh Local, November 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - DSA Constitution and Bylaws, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Committees and National Boards, 1983-1990; III.
  - DSA/Pittsburgh Committees, January 1983-November 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Contains list of 1984 committee leadership, Labor and Urban Politics, Political Action Committee endorsements, Allegheny Socialist Committee, Ad Hoc Committee.
  - DSA Committees, September 1983-August 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Robert Opie Shepherd collected information from national DSA committees. These include the National Interim, National Executive, International Affairs, National Political Action, and the Negotiating Committees. Also contains a Directory of Locals and Organizing Committees.
  - DSA National Board, November 1987-July 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Contains Proposed Procedures for Resolutions at National Board Meeting, and minutes from 1988 National Board meeting.
- DSA Conferences and Conventions, 1983-1990; IV.
  - Regional Conferences, January 1984-August 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    DSA/Pittsburgh participated in several DSA conferences. Information from the Mechanicsburg, Heartland Regional, and Bloomsburg conferences are included in the series.
  - National Convention, July 1983-December 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    Robert Opie Shepherd attended four national conventions as a delegate representing the DSA/Pittsburgh.
  - National Convention, March 1989-August 1990 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    Contains materials from the 1983 New York Convention, 1984 Philadelphia Convention, 1989 Baltimore Convention, and 1990 Youth Section Summer Conference.
- Projects and Events, 1982-1990; V.
  - Events Sponsored by DSA, 1983-1990; 1.
    - Events Sponsored by DSA/Pittsburgh, December 1983, October 1987-August 1990 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      DSA/Pittsburgh sponsored events in the Pittsburgh area, including a Billy Bragg concert, voter registration campaign, and Women's Day awards. File also contains various event announcements.
    - Events Supported by DSA/Pittsburgh, June 1988-November 1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      DSA/Pittsburgh supported many events sponsored by other organizations, yet reflecting the goals of the DSA. Contains statements, information, and announcements regarding the Chinese democracy movement, April 15th Coalition, and other events.
    - Events Sponsored by Other DSA Locals, May 1988-May 1990 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Events Sponsored by DSA, June 1982, June 1988-November 1990 (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
      Contains material from the Working Group on Health Care and American Solidarity Campaign, and announcements for conferences, marches, rallies, and other Socialist issues.
    - Events Supported by the DSA, April 1983, June 1988-November 1990 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      DSA supported many activities and projects sponsored by groups with goals related to those of the DSA. Contains boycott and rally announcements, labor bulletins, and information from the Institute for Democratic Socialism (IDS).
  - Nicaraguan Delegation, general, 1982 - 1983; 2.
    - Notes Recorded by Robert Opie Shepherd, January 1983 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      The DSA sponsored a fact-finding tour to Nicaragua from January 15, 1983 to January 22, 1983. Robert Opie Shepherd was one of the twenty-four delegates participating in the tour.
    - Reports, June 1982, January 1983 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Contains DSA Report on Nicaragua and Women in Nicaragua.
  - Government Publications, Nicaraguan Delegation, undated; 3.
    - Ministerio de Salud, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
      The Nicaraguan government published a series of pamphlets to educate the public. This series contains pamphlets regarding personal hygiene and health issues.
    - Miscellaneous Government Publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
      This file includes the Biographia de Camilo Ortega, Discurso del Comandante, Manifesto de San Albino, 1981 Ano de la Defensa y la Produccion, and Relacions de la Contabilid con los Trabejadores.
  - Publications, Nicaraguan Delegation, 1981-1982; 4.
    - El Muchacho de Niguinohomo, by S. Ramirez, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Guatemala: The People Unite!: Unitary Statement from the Guatemalan National Revolutionary Unity (URNG) and Declaration of the Guatemalan Patriotic Unity Committee (CGUP), January 1982
    - I Cristo Ya Ha Venido!, by the Instituto Historico Centro Americano, n.d.
    - Que es un Sandinista?, by Fonseca, Turicios, and Morales, 1980
    - Women and the Nicaraguan Revolution, by T. Borge, Reprint edition, November 1982
  - Pamphlets, Nicaraguan Delegation, 1981; 5.
    - El Salvador: Women in Revolution, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Medical Aid for El Salvador, undated
    - Money for Jobs, Not War!, by Central American Mobilization Coalization, undated
    - Nicaragua: Supporting the Revolution, 1981
    - Tasba Pri: Labla de la Revolucion, by INNICA, undated
    - Where Can an Undocumented Refugee from Central America Receive Health Care in Los Angeles?, by Clinica Oscar A. Romero, undated
  - Newspapers and Articles, Nicaraguan Delegation, 1982-1983; 6.
    - Newspapers and Articles, August 1982, September 1983-December 1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Contains Nicaragua: A Look at the Reality, September 1983; La Semana Comica, December 1983; and Trabajadores, No. 13.
  - Miscellaneous Information, Nicaraguan Delegation, November 1982; 7.
    - Miscellaneous Information, November 1982 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Contains Robert Opie Shepherd's application for tour, reading list, glossary, chart of Nicaraguan government, and post cards.
- Publications, 1982-1990; VI.
  - DSA Publication, 1977-1990; 1.
    - DSA/Pittsburgh Monthly Newsheets, October 1982-June 1990 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Missing: December 1982-October 1983
      January 1984-March 1984
      December 1984-November 1985
      January 1986-May 1987
      July 1987-September 1987
      November 1987-December 1987
      September 1988-November 1988
      January 1989-June 1989
      August 1989-December 1989
      February 1990-May 1990
    - Democratic Socialists of America, Formerly New American Movement/Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee, Pittsburgh Local Newsletter, Volume 10, Number 4, September 1982-October 1982 (Box 3, Folder 33-34)
      Issued 1973 through May/June 1982 as New American Movement, Pittsburgh Chapter Newsletter; changed title with November/December 1982 - 1990 to Allegheny Socialist. For copies of the New American Movement, Pittsburgh Chapter Newsletter, see
      ais 89:18
      .
    - Newsletters of Other DSA Locals, July 1981-October 1990 (Box 3, Folder 35-37)
      Contains Cleveland Beacon (July 1981-1983), Forward Left (April 1988-February 1990), Ithaca Socialist (August 1988 and November 1989), Kentucky Socialist (August 1988), New Ground (May 1988-June 1990), New York Democratic Socialist (n.d.), Philadelphia Socialist (September 1988-October 1990), The Reading Socialist (November 1983-January 1984).
    - Democratic Left, November 1977, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 37a - b)
      Issued November 1977 as Newsletter of the Democratic Left Missing: December 1977-August 1980; October-December 1980; February-March 1981; May 1981-September 1982; February 1983; June-August 1983; November 1983-February 1984; May-June 1984; September 1984-April 1987; November 1987-February 1988; July-August 1988.
  - Commission Publications, 2.
    - Environmental Commission, Spring-Summer 1990 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Contains EcoSocialist Review, Volume 4, Numbers 1-2.
    - Labor Commission, February 1988-December 1988
      Contains Labor Voice, February 1988, August 1988, October 1988, and December 1988.
    - Latino, Afro-American and Anti-Racism Commission, Summer 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      Contains Our Struggle/Nuestra Lucha, Volume 6, Numbers 2 and 3; Volume 7, Spring 1989; Volume 8, Numbers 2 and 3.
    - Religion and Socialism Commission, Fall 1988, Summer 1989
      Contains Religious Socialism, Volume 12, Number 3, and Volume 13, Number 2.
    - Youth Section, January 1988-August 1990
      Contains Activist (Numbers 12, 24, and 25); Days of Decision (Winter 1988); A Better World in Birth, Songs for Socialists.
  - Special Publications and Pamphlets, 3.
    - DSA-Los Nuevos Socialists, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Feminist Perspectives on the Family, Volume 10, Summer 1982
    - The Near and the Far: What it Means to be a Socialist in America Today
    - Plant Closings = Jobs Blackmail, n.d.
    - The Politics of the Housing Crisis, n.d.
    - Revolution and Democracy
    - Socialism Informs: The Best of Our Politics, n.d.
    - Socialist Standard, Volume 1, Number 5; Volume 2, Numbers 2 and 4; Volume 4, Numbers 4-5, 1983-1986
    - Socialist Vision, n.d.
    - "Some Rob You with a Six Gun, Some with a Fountain Pen," A Democratic Socialist Perspective on the Savings and Loan Crisis
    - We are Democratic Socialists with a Vision for the Future, n.d.
    - What is Socialist Feminism?, 1986
    - What Socialism is...and is not: Twelve Myths About Democratic Socialism
    - Where We Stand: A Political Statement of Democratic Socialists of America
    - Why We are Socialists: Points of Unity Between the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee and the New American Movement
  - Other Publications, 1988-1989; 4.
    - The Commonwealth Report: A Newsletter of Politics and Public Opinion, The Commonwealth Institute, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      Contains issues dated May/June 1989 and September 1989.
    - Democratic Promise: Ideas for Turning America in a Progressive Direction, Foundation for the Study of Independent Social Ideas, 1988
    - Left Green Notes: Organizing Bulletin of the Left Green Network, January 1989, Number 1
    - UAW Ammo: What Next for Polish Workers?, Volume 26, Number 8, n.d.
  - Institute for Democratic Socialism, 1984-1990; 5.
    - The Black Church and Marxism: What Do They Have to Say to Each Other?, James H. Cone, April 1980 (Box 4, Folder 40a-d)
    - Socialist Forum: Discussion Bulletin of the Democratic Socialists of America, Institute for Democratic Socialism, 1984-1990
      Contains Number 4, Part 1 and supplement; Number 5, 1984; Number 11, 1987; Number 13, 1988; Number 14 and Number 15, 1989; Number 16, 1990.
    - Third World Socialists: A Political Journal on the Theory and Practice of Liberation
      Contains Volume 1, Numbers 1-2.
    - Toward a Socialist Theory of Racism, Cornel West, n.d.
- Memorandum and Information from DSA, 1984-1990; VII.
  - Correspondence from DSA to DSA/Pittsburgh, October 1984-November 1990 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    Contains memorandum, issue updates, event announcements, policy status sheets, and any information relevant to all general members.
  - Membership and Finances, August 1986-February 1990 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    Includes DSA/Pittsburgh membership, DSA general members in Pittsburgh area, 1990 budget, and 1989 mailing schedule.
  - News Articles, October 1983-October 1990 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    The DSA frequently sent news articles to the Locals regarding issues of concern for the Democratic Socialists. The subjects of the articles include poverty, abortion rights, candidates, environment, and the role of Socialism in American politics.
- Reports and Miscellaneous Subject Files, 1982-1990; VIII.
  - Reports, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    DSA members and committees generated several unpublished reports regarding issues of concern for Democratic Socialists. The file contains The Corporate Compromise: A Marxist View of Health Policy, The Ecological Argument for Socialism, Report to National Office, State of the World 1990, and Towards Pay Equity: A Workers Guide to Fighting Wage Discrimination.
  - Michael Harrington and General Correspondence, 1982-1990 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    Michael Harrington, a respected author and Socialist leader, was a founder and co-chair of the DSA. The file contains articles, a brief outline of accomplishments, obituaries, memorial service announcements as well as general correspondence.
  - Miscellaneous, December 1989-March 1990 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    Contains job opening announcements, CAREPAC list, 1990 Official and Unofficial Leadership of DSA/Pittsburgh, quotes, memo to Citizen Action, and DSA logos.